Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Fox, Abe: Audio Recording, 1973 July 3 (Cassette 46A, 46B & 47, Box 13, Reel 47A-47B, Box 5, Reel 46A-46B)
    Abe Fox was born in Russia in 1890. He was one of eight children, with four brothers and three sisters. His father made and sold glass windows. Fox attended school in Russia for two years before apprenticing to a tailor. He immigrated to the United States in 1906 and lived on the East Side of Manhattan, New York before moving to the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1916. He married when he was around 20 years old and had three children. He worked as a tailor in various shops in New York City and was an active member of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union Local 23.
    This interview was conducted by Mark Hirsch on July 3, 1973 at Abe Fox’s home. Fox’s accent, his tendency to mumble, and the fluctuation of volume over the course of the interview make him hard to understand. The interview covers Fox’s childhood in Russia; his immigration to the United States (US) in 1906; and his work in the garment industry in New York, New York. Fox begins the interview by describing his childhood in Russia, focusing on anti-Semitism in his hometown, which included pogroms and abuse by the police. He recounts not being paid during the three years of his tailoring apprenticeship and receiving meager pay for his long hours of work after his apprenticeship. He recounts the Socialist Revolutionary Party meeting at his house and learning more about Socialism at the library until his library card was destroyed when it was learned that he was Jewish.
    Fox explains that he immigrated to the US in 1906 after several failed attempts to illegally cross the border into Austria in order to sail from a port in Poland. He discusses living with his aunt’s family on the East Side of Manhattan, recalling his acclimation to the spring weather and the low cost of food in New York City. He describes his first job in a garment shop in New York City and explains that, in the beginning, he had to bring his own machine to work. He notes that although he joined the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union (ILGWU) Local 23 in order to fight for better wages, hours, and working conditions, change was slow due to factions within the union and corruption among the union leaders. He recalls a strike that occurred in the early 1950s, through which workers acquired a twenty percent wage increase despite conflicts with strikebreakers brought in from Chicago, Illinois. He discusses the ILGWU opening a school to train machine operators and the union becoming more inclusive, particularly in terms of the Italian population’s involvement. He explains that different skill levels and job types had different wage standards in the union and discusses working conditions in the garment shops. He recounts that he established a ready-made garment store on Pitkin Avenue in Brooklyn with his brother and step-father, noting that the people paid to guard the store broke in and stole all the merchandise.
    Other topics include a comparison of his impression of the US before and after his immigration; his tumultuous relationships with his father and step-father; his lack of knowledge regarding pregnancy and sex prior to his marriage; his leisure activities, including reading the newspaper, playing pinochle, and attending shows at the Jewish theater; and his views on the birth control movement, the rise of political power among the Cuban and black populations, and the migration of Jews to the suburbs.
    See also: Life Before Immigration or Migration; Interview Compilation for Radio Broadcast; and Passage.
    International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 23-25 (New York, N.Y.).; Antisemitism |z Russia |x History |y 20th century.; Pogroms |z Russia |x History |y 20th century.
  - Fox, Abe: Subject Cards, 1973 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fox, Gladys, 1975 (Box 14, Cassette 214 & 214A)
    Gladys Fox was born on the island of Nevis in Saint Kitts and Nevis. She worked as a teacher until she immigrated to the United States in 1947. After her immigration, Fox worked in a dry cleaners and as a pediatric nurses’ aide before studying early childhood development at Fordham University in the Bronx, New York. She worked at Morrisania Hospital in the Bronx until she retired in 1972 and was a member of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union.
    The interview with Gladys Fox was conducted by Jay Facciolo in 1975 at an unknown location. The main subjects of this interview include Fox’s life and career in the British West Indies, her immigration to the United States (US), and her work in the US healthcare system after her immigration. Fox discusses her life in Saint Kitts and Nevis, including being the youngest of seven children; her father working as a carpenter and being away from the family because of his work; and learning to read, write, and perform multiplication and division by the age of four. She recalls beginning the process of becoming a teacher in the British West Indies at 15 years old, and becoming frustrated with her lack of advancement after teaching for over 20 years. She mentions her immigration; the fact that she initially came to the US with no intention of staying permanently; and the fact that she was required to leave the country through Canada before she could become a citizen. She recounts living with her two older sisters in the US, and feeling that she was imposing because she was over 40 years old when she immigrated. She discusses having trouble finding well paying work; receiving a certificate to be a pediatric nurses' aide; and studying early childhood education at Fordham University in the Bronx. She discusses working for hospitals such as the Flowers Fifth Avenue Hospital in Valhalla, New York; St. Luke's Hospital in Manhattan, New York; and Morrisania Hospital in the Bronx, New York.
    Fox elaborates on her time at Morrisania Hospital, including the fact that she was quickly given a supervisory position. Fox recalls that there were disagreements between the staff at Morrisania Hospital and workers contracted from Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx, because of differences in pay; and becoming a member of the Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union. She also mentions that she still worked for the Local 1199 at the time of the interview as a corresponding secretary, sending birthday cards to retirees; attending conferences; and serving on a number of committees.
  - Frasca, Corrado, Undated (Box 1, Box 12, Cassette 175)
    Corrado Frasca was born in Pollago, Italy on February 6, 1908. His father died when he was six months old and his mother remarried. He had two sisters and one step-brother, all of whom remained in Italy. Frasca married and had one son. He spent most of his life as a longshoreman but also worked as peddler, grocer, and brewer of moonshine.
    This interview was conducted by John Jentz and Frank Farragaso at a senior citizen center on Court Street in Brooklyn, New York (likely the Carroll Park Senior Center). The date of the interview is unknown. This interview covers Corrado Frasca’s childhood in Pollago Italy; his illegal immigration to the United States (US) in 1926; and his life and work as a longshoreman in Brooklyn. Frasca begins this interview by describing his childhood in Pollago, Italy, recalling doing simple jobs for the local fishermen and seamen when he was eight years old. He explains that he moved to Genoa when he was twelve and worked for several years aboard a passenger ship. He discusses an uncle in New York encouraging him to come to the United States, and Frasca jumping ship in Norfolk, Virginia in 1926. He describes traveling to Baltimore, Maryland to avoid the authorities and locals who spoke Italian coming to his aid by giving him room and board free of charge. Frasca explains that his uncle brought him to Brooklyn where he began working as a longshoreman. He describes shifting occupations depending on the seasons; working on ships going to South America in the winter; working as a longshoreman in Brooklyn during the rest of the year; and later establishing his own business as a peddler and fruit seller. Frasca mentions joining a club established by immigrants from his hometown and the club providing social and fiscal support to its members during hard times. He describes how he met his wife, an American citizen, through his uncle, who served as a matchmaker in their apartment building.
    Throughout the interview, Frasca describes a tension between his Italian heritage and his new life in the US, including his refusal to be stationed in Italy during World War II for fear of fighting his family and the way in which he gradually learned English through his wife and conversations he had with non-Italian longshoremen with whom he worked. He describes the differences between his generation and his son’s generation, noting his opinion that the younger generation is less social and less attached to traditional family values.
  - Fulwood, Ophelia, 1975 December 17 (Box 6, Cassette 205)
    Ophelia Fullwood was born in Morganton, North Carolina. She migrated north in 1941 and worked in Dover, Delaware and New York, New York. She worked in an ammunition factory and as a maid in private homes and hotels. She was employed as a maid at the time of the interview. She was a member of the Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union Local 6.
    This interview was conducted in the Bronx, New York by Sasha Silverstein on December 7, 1975. Main topics include Ophelia Fulwood’s life in North Carolina, her migration north, her work as a maid, and her union activities. Fullwood recalls her early years in North Carolina including being raised by her mother’s cousin; giving water to the workers on her grandfather’s farm during the harvest season; leaving school in eighth grade to work as a maid; and learning about sex. Some of her first impressions of New York, New York include being shocked by the segregation in the US; not having warm clothes; and being afraid to be alone in New York City. She discusses her work as a maid, including her work schedule; the fact that she quit her job when her employers had marital problems; and that employment opportunities often came by word of mouth. When discussing her feelings on being a maid, Fulwood mentioned preferring day labor over sleep-in positions; that she loved being able to control her own schedule at the time of the interview; and that she was firm during the hiring process about what type of work she would do and how much she should be paid for it.
    Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union. Local 6 (Hotel, Restaurant and Club Employees Union) (New York, N.Y.).; African American women household employees |v Interviews.
  - Galinas, Mary MacCarthy: Audio Recording, 1973 April 16 (Box 21, Cassette 225)
    Mary MacCarthy Galinas was born on a farm in the late 1890s in County Kerry, Ireland and was the eldest of six children. She lived in Dublin, Ireland and London, England before immigrating to the United States in 1926, where she lived in Boston, Massachusetts and New York, New York. She worked as a waitress and married a French Canadian cook, with whom she had one daughter.
    This interview was recorded on April 16, 1973 at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York by an unspecified interviewer. The interview covers Mary MacCarthy Galinas’ early life in Ireland and Great Britain, her immigration to the United States (US), her working life, and her family. Galinas recounts leaving her home in County Kerry, Ireland to care for her uncle’s family in Dublin; moving to London, England to live with her sister; and remembering London as a place where British, Irish, and Scots all lived together harmoniously. She recounts her pride in being able to save a great deal of money before immigrating to the US. Topics regarding her life in Boston, Massachusetts include meeting her husband in one of the restaurants where she worked; continuing to work after her marriage and the birth of her daughter; and being unable to continue to save money after her marriage and the theft of her savings. Her discussion of New York, New York includes her decision to move there in the 1940s to gain better education opportunities for her daughter.
  - Galinas, Mary MacCarthy: Transcript, 1973 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gavin, Jimmy, Undated (Box 27, Box 17, Cassette 230, 230A- 230C)
  - Geiss, Amelia, 1974 April 19 (Box 25, Cassette 246)
    Amelia Geiss was born in Hanover, Germany in 1909. She immigrated to the United States in 1929. She settled in New York, New York, where she met and married her husband. She worked mainly in restaurants and volunteered at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan after her retirement.
    This interview was conducted on April 19, 1974 by Scott Weir at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan, New York. The majority of this interview, covering the first 25 years of Amelia Geiss’ life, was not recorded. Topics covered include Geiss’ relationship with her husband; her experiences during the Great Depression; racial and ethnic tensions in her community in New York, New York; and her work at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center. Geiss spends the majority of the interview discussing her relationship with her husband, Bill, including how he was separated from his first wife when they first began their relationship; the fact that his estranged wife stalked Geiss; and the fact that she moved multiple times to escape this harassment. She discusses her husband's work as an electrician at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. She recalls that they survived the Great Depression due to the fact that they both were able to work. She discusses the community she lived in at the time of the interview, including how ethnic discrimination had gotten worse over time, and that the community had more problems at the time of the interview because it was no longer predominantly German. She discusses her volunteer work at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center, including the fact that she joined so that she and her husband would not fight after they retired; her fundraising efforts; both she and her husband being recognized by New York City for their work at the Center; and her participation on the Board of Directors.
  - Geller, Bessie, 1991 (Box 8, Reel 83A-83B, Reel 84A-84B, Cassette 83, 84A-B)
  - Gelo, Grace: Audio Recording, 1974 (Box 1, Box 7, Cassette 160A-B)
    Grace Gelo was born in 1900 in Tunis, Tunisia. Her father was born in Sicily, Italy and immigrated to Tunisia after his military service in Italy. He worked as a shoemaker. Her mother was born in Sicily and immigrated as a small child with her family to Tunisia. The family immigrated to the United States (US) in 1914 and lived in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York.
    Gelo worked in the garment industry and was a member of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union (ILGWU). She married John Gelo, who was born in Italy and immigrated to the US in 1907. He was a member, organizer, and official of the ILGWU Local 89. He was a delegate of the American Labor Party and of the ILGWU. They lived in Brooklyn and had three daughters.
    This interview was conducted by Janice Albert in 1974 at an unspecified location. The interview covers Grace Gelo’s childhood in Tunis, Tunisia; her immigration to the United States (US); her working life; her husband’s union and political activity; and their children. Gelo discusses her childhood in Tunis, including her education and her parents’ backgrounds. She provides a short history of the colonization of Tunisia and of the ethnic groups in Tunis. She discusses her family’s immigration to the US and the ethnic groups in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She discusses her strict upbringing and rules her father imposed upon her; her courtship with her husband under these rules; and her younger sister’s rebellion against the rules. She discusses having to leave school in order to work to support her family and working as a finisher on men’s clothes. She describes the first factory in which she worked; the ethnic demographics of the workers, mainly Italian and Jewish, and the language barrier between the two groups; and her unhappiness in her work and her difficulty communicating with the Jewish workers. She describes working conditions in the factories; her dissatisfaction with them; and her opinion that the workers were seriously mistreated.
    Gelo discusses her husband’s union and political activity; his participation in early organizing efforts of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union (ILGWU), particularly in 1909, and his election as a delegate of the American Labor Party (ALP). She discusses attending conventions with her husband, including American Federation of Labor national conventions, ILGWU national conventions, and political conventions as a delegate of the ALP. Other topics include her father’s insistence that his children retain their Italian identity in both Tunisia and US; her participation in social activities at the time of the interview; and her daughters.
    See also: Life Before Immigration or Migration; and Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York,New York and the United States.
    International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 89 (New York, N.Y.).; Italians |z Tunisia |x History |y 20th century.
  - Gelo, Grace: Index, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gelo, Grace: Summary, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Glick, Hyman: Audio Recording, Undated (Box 13, Reel 58A-58B, Cassette 58)
    Hyman Glick was born Hyman Gleot in Vilna, Russia in 1883. He had five brothers and two sisters. His father was a teacher at a cheder, or Jewish elementary school. Glick attended university and married in Dvinsk, Russia. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1902 and changed his name to Glick. He lived in the US for three years before his wife immigrated with their son.
    The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. One of Hyman Glick’s grandsons assists in the interview but is not identified by name. The interview covers Glick’s childhood in Vilna, Russia; his immigration to the United States (US); his working life; and his family. Glick discusses his education at a cheder in Vilna until the age of 18 and at a university in Dvinsk, Russia where he studied chemistry and trained as a dyer. He discusses his wife and mother-in-law deciding for him to immigrate to the US in order to avoid being drafted into the Russian Army; living with his wife’s relatives in the US; and his wife’s uncle deciding he should change his name from Gleot to Glick because it was easier to spell. He recounts finding and losing jobs in different industries before settling in the dry cleaning industry; the salary he received; and the number of days he worked per week at these jobs. He discusses borrowing money in order to bring his wife and son over to the US and living in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. He recounts his business ventures, including buying two dry cleaning stores in Manhattan and buying and selling dry cleaning stores in order to make a profit. Other topics include attending movies and the Yiddish theater on Sundays and collecting clothes from customers with a horse and wagon in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    Dry cleaning industry |x Employees |z New York (State)
  - Glick, Hyman: Subject Cards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Godet, Rose, 1973 April 24 (Cassette 210, Box 18)
    Rose Godet was born in the Dominican Republic in 1896. She was of French descent. She immigrated to the United States with her father in 1919. She worked in Manhattan, New York for the Charles Broadway Rouss department store as a saleswoman, as a translator for a mail order company, and as a packager for the National Biscuit Company.
    This interview was conducted on April 24, 1973 by Victor Scheluchin at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens, on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. The main topics discussed include Rose Godet’s childhood in the Dominican Republic, her feelings about immigrating to the United States (US), her work experience, and her personal experiences in New York, New York. Godet begins by discussing her early life in the Dominican Republic, including being of French descent; speaking multiple languages; and her father working for the Puccini Shipping Company. Her early experiences in New York City include living on 140th Street in Manhattan; deciding to only live in Manhattan; disliking living in the US initially because she had never worked before; feeling lonely in the city; and finding the US to be substantially more expensive than the Dominican Republic. Godet discusses her confusion regarding segregation, having never witnessed white flight before coming to the US. She discusses her personal experiences during the Prohibition era and the Great Depression, including an Irish friend giving her bootleg liquor, though she did not like the taste; enjoying visiting speakeasies; and being employed pressing silk underwear. She talks about World War II and her fear of air raid drills; that minimum wage requirements implemented by Franklin Roosevelt were not enforced; and her belief that the US government would pull men off the streets and force them into the military. She notes her work experience, which included working as a saleswoman and interpreter for the Charles Broadway Rouss department store on Broadway in Manhattan and learning to type in order to work for a mail order company translating orders received in Spanish or French. She discusses her employment at the National Biscuit Company packing cookies after she began to lose her eyesight, and feeling exploited by the company due to the minimal vacation time, long hours, and low wages.
    Prohibition |z New York (State) |z New York; Segregation |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Goldman, Minna: Audio Recording, 1974 April 18 (Box 8, Reel 82A-82B, Cassette 82)
    Minna Goldman was born in Bucharest, Romania in the late 19th century and was the eldest of seven children. She immigrated to the United States (US) and returned to Romania twice before settling permanently in the US. Her first immigration to the US was in 1907 with her father and younger brother, who died in the Netherlands during their travels. Goldman and her father settled in New York, New York, where her father worked as an umbrella maker and she worked in a blouse factory. They returned to Romania after six months in the US. Goldman returned to the US in 1910 with a cousin and worked refurbishing old umbrellas. She saved enough money to buy passage for her parents and five siblings though they declined to travel. She returned to Romania in 1912 and resumed her education. After leaving school, she worked in a foreign language bookstore and for the American Red Cross in Bucharest. She returned to the US in 1920. She worked in a bank before meeting her husband, who was a pharmacist and owned a pharmacy. She worked in the pharmacy until the birth of their daughter. After the death of her husband, she worked for the Jewish Labor Committee in Manhattan.